Finding Aid of the Dave Berkman Papers, 1958-2016
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Dave Berkman Papers, 1958-2016
Berkman, Dave, 1934-2015
UWM Manuscript Collection 347
3.4 cubic ft. (5 boxes, including 38 audio cassettes) 1 videocassette 448 digital audio files (22 GB)
University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee Libraries, Archives Department
Papers of former UWM professor and media critic Dave Berkman consisting of articles, including copies of his Shepherd Express "Media Musings," news clippings, correspondence, and an extensive set of radio broadcasts, largely Wisconsin Public Radio recordings.
Dave Berkman (1934-2015) was a college professor and media critic. Berkman taught mass communications at UW-Milwaukee, among other universities. For many years he wrote a column called "Media Musings" for the Shepherd Express, a Milwaukee alternative paper. He also hosted Wisconsin Public Radio's "Media Talk" show for 13 years.
Berkman was a liberal, a civil rights activist, and a free speech absolutist, and served on the state boards of the ACLU in Wisconsin and Connecticut, as well as on the Corporation for Public Broadcasting's Minority Task Force. Berkman was a member of the National Association of Educational Broadcasters, and advocated protecting Public Broadcasting's independence from political threats. He was a man of strong opinions who loved politics and argument.
The paper files largely consist of correspondence, copies of Berkman's "Media Musings" in Milwaukee's Shepherd Express alternative newspaper, publications and articles, and clipping files. The collection also includes Berkman's 1963 dissertation, as well as various reports, including information about the work of the Corporation for Public Broadcasting's Minority Task Force on which Berkman served.
The radio broadcasts, largely Wisconsin Public Radio recordings, cover a wide variety of local and national topics, many of which concern meta-analysis of media coverage of events. Most of the electronic recordings in the collection are of Berkman's Media Talk show on Wisconsin Public Radio (2003-2006), which took a weekly look at how issues such as Global Warming, Hurricane Katrina, the 2003 Iraq War, the 2004 presidential election, and the Judith Miller/Scooter Libby intelligence disclosure scandal were covered by national and Wisconsin media. Berkman also frequently guest-hosted for fellow WPR correspondents Eric Vonn, Joy Cardin, and Ben Merens; as befitting Berkman's speciality, most of these shows also dealt with media and political issues, such as the makeup of the African-American Vote, the Wisconsin Primary's effect on Super Tuesday 2004, and U.S. Energy policy. Both of these shows often featured prominent guests from the media and political worlds, including Kathleen Parker, Terry Neal, Eugene Kane, James Wolcott, and Chris Bowers, as well as local Wisconsin journalists and activists such as Tim Cuprisin, Bill Lueders, Craig Gilbert, Mordecai Lee, and Stan Stojkovic. A small number of electronic recordings are of shows on which Berkman appeared as a guest himself, mostly as part of a weekly media panel on the Eric Vonn show.
The audio cassettes mainly consist of Media Talk broadcasts. There are several cassettes that consist of shows that Berkman hosted and Berkman being a guest on the Kathleen Dunn Show and the Ben Merens Show. Topics discussed on the shows include the Jesse Anderson case, Jeffrey Dahmer case, Laurie Bembenek, Second Amendment, media influence on society, quality of journalism, labor union issues, and politics.
The videocassette consists of an episode of the show Conservative Forum. As the guest on the show, Berkman discussed his views on the United States' military presence in the world.
The files are arranged into the following series:
Subject Files, 1958-2016
Radio Broadcasts, 1991-2009
Media Talk, 1991-2006
Guest Hosting Appearances, 1997-2007
Other Appearances, 1991-2009
A spreadsheet with detailed information about the electronic recordings is available in the Archives. The spreadsheet includes information about the show for which the recordings were made, the title/topic of the show, the featured guests, the date of broadcast, and the approximate duration of the recording. Additional technical metadata is available in the Archives; consult an archivist for more details.
Related Material in the UWM Libraries
UW-Milwaukee Dept. of Mass Communication UWM Archival Collection 179
UW-Milwaukee University Relations Records UWM Archival Collection 96
Administrative/Restriction Information
There are no access restrictions on the materials, and the collection is open to all members of the public in accordance with state law.
Margarita Dusek donated the collection to the Archives in September and November 2016 (accession 2016-015).
As of November 22, 2016, all electronic files were accessible on a Intel Core i5-4570 CPU (3.20 GHz, 4 GB RAM) running Windows 7 Enterprise, with Service Pack 1. Windows Media Player was used to access the files.
The collection includes records in the following formats:
MPEG 1/2 Audio Layer 3 [.mp3]
Plain Text [.txt]
AppleWorks Word Processing File [.cwk]
Microsoft Word 2007 onwards [.docx]
Contents List
- Records, 1958-2016, UWM Manuscript Collection 347; 4.2 cubic ft. (5 boxes, including 38 audio cassettes) 1 videocassette 448 digital audio files (22 GB)
  - 1. Subject Files, 1958-2016
    - Address, Medgar Evers College, 1979 (Box 3)
    - Clippings, 1958-2016 (Box 3)
    - Conservative Forum, undated, 1 videocassette (VHS) (Video 1)
    - Corporation for Public Broadcasting's Minority Task Force, 1978-1981 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence, 1960-2015 (Box 1)
    - Dissertation, 1963 (Box 3)
    - ITV Business Development Project, 1969 (Box 4)
    - Manuscript, Report, and Survey, 1978-1989 (Box 3)
    - Media Musings, Shepherd Express, 1989-2006 (Box 2)
    - Publications/Articles, 1962-2006 (Box 2)
    - Vita, 2010 (Box 3)
  - 2. Radio Broadcasts, 1991-2009
    The recordings in each subseries are arranged chronologically by date of broadcast. Audio numbers under recordings signify physical audio cassettes; "ID No." under recordings signifies digital files accessible in the Archives. See an archivist for more information.
    - A. Media Talk, 1991-2006
      - Bambi, Laurie Bembenek, 17 June 1991, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 1)
        With Tom Clark, political correspondent
      - Wisconsin News Magazine on Coverage of Dahmer Case, 4 August 1991, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 1)
      - Dennis Getto, Restaurant Critic, Milwaukee Journal, 19 September 1993, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 2)
      - Twentieth Century Fund Report on Future of Public Television, 19 September 1993, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 2)
        With Richard Somerset-Ward, Author
      - Coverage on Breitlow Murder, 12 December 1993, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 3)
        With Jim Romenesko, journalist
      - Evolution of Television, 12 December 1993, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 3)
        With Lardy Laurent, Critic Emeritus, Washington Post
      - 'Electronic Violence' and Kids, 13 December 1993, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 4)
        With Tom Clark, Wisconsin Public Radio
      - Bobby Inman, Press Criticisms, 19 January 1994, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 4)
        With Kathleen Dunn, Wisconsin Public Radio
      - Christian Broadcasting, 10 April 1994, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 5)
        With Vic Eliason, Founder, VCY America Radio Network
      - Court TV and Legal Reporting, 10 April 1994, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 5)
        With Fred Graham, Court TV
      - All American Television, Inc. Syndicates 'Baywatch', 15 May 1994, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 6)
        With Paul Siegel, President
      - Gossip Columning, 15 May 1994, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 6)
        With Meg Kissinger, journalist
      - Open Line, 6 August 1994, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 7)
      - Psychic Phenomenon Invasion of Media, 6 August 1994, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 7)
        With James Randi, magician and scientific skeptic
      - By Invitation Only: How the Media Limit the Political Debate, 22 January 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 8)
        With David Croteau, author
      - Critic on Journal Sentinel, 22 January 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 8)
        With Jim Romenesko, Journalist
      - Morning Sports Talk, 26 February 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 9)
        With Scott Aebly, co-host
      - Role of Alternative Paper in a One-Daily Town, 26 February 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 9)
        With Greg Quindel and Doug Hissom, Shepherd Express
      - First Month of New Journal Sentinel, 30 April 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 10)
      - Let's Go Buy New Paper, 30 April 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 10)
        With Joel McNally, journalist
      - John Heckenlively, Reporter, Racine Labor, 11 June 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 11)
      - David Niles, Editor, Small Business Times, 11 June 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 11)
      - Freedom Forum Paper on Fairness, 24 September 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 12)
        With Will Pinkston, Author
      - Journal Sentinel Merger, 24 September 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 12)
      - William Elliott, Dean Designate, Marquette University, 22 October 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 13)
      - WKLH's Dave Luczak and Carole Caine, 22 October 1995, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 13)
      - Differences in Black and White Television Viewing, 9 June 1996, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 14)
        With Eugene Kane, journalist
      - Girls and Kid Videos, 9 June 1996, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 14)
        With Jennifer Magnan, journalist
      - Nick Carter, Rock Critic and Nightlife Columnist, Milwaukee Journal Sentinel, 7 July 1996, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 15)
      - Briggs and Stratton $630 Million Libel Suit, 7 July 1996, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 15)
        With Tom Fox, editor
      - Scott Dikkers, Founder, The Onion, 16 October 1998, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 16)
      - How Right Wing Foundations Set the Media's Agenda, 16 October 1998, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 16)
        With Lawrence Soley, Journalist
      - Milwaukee Press Club, 14 July 2000, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 17)
        With Mark Zoromski and Leo Kissel, journalists
      - WORT's Twenty-fifth Anniversary, 14 July 2000, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 17)
        With Norman Stockwell, journalist
      - How Manhattan-Based Media Control the National News Agenda, 27 April 2001, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 18)
        With Brent Cunningham, editor
      - Roll of Wisconsin Public Radio Producers, 4 May 2001, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 18)
        With Ben Merens, journalist
      - Future of Wisconsin Public Radio, 25 May 2001, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 19)
        With Gregg Schnirring, Wisconsin Public Radio
      - How Federal Communications Commission Has Changed, 1 June 2001, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 19)
        With Nick Johnson, former commissioner, Federal Communications Commission
      - Media Coverage on Twin Towers and the Pentagon Terrorist Attacks, 13 September 2001, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 20)
      - Television Coverage of Terrorist Attacks on New York City and Pentagon, 14 September 2001, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 20)
        With Tim Cuprisin, journalist
      - Calling for Strong Military Response to Twin Towers Terrorism, 21 September 2001, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 21)
        With James Hirst, journalist
      - Listener Reactions to Media Coverage of Terrorist Acts, 21 September 2001, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 21)
      - Poll Showing Public Distrust of Press Back to Pre-9/11 Level, 16 August 2002, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 22)
        With Carroll Doherty, Pew Research Center
      - Television News in Aftermath of 9/11 and First Anniversary, 6 September 2002, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 22)
      - Black and White Divide on Support for Iraqi War, 19 April 2003, audio cassette (Box 5, Audio 23)
        With Eugene Kane, Journalist
      - Newspaper Ombudsmen, 30 May 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:50:51) (Electronic 1)
        With Don Wycliff, Chicago Tribune public editor
      - Media Wars: News at a Time of Terror, 20 June 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:50:30) (Electronic 2)
        With Danny Schechter, Author
      - Open Line, 27 June 2003, 1 digital audio file (1:13:48) (Electronic 3)
      - Bush Admin. Bullies Press, 04 July 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:42:36) (Electronic 4)
        With James Wolcott, Vanity Fair
      - Last FCC Ruling, 18 July 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:47:04) (Electronic 5)
        With John Dunbar, Center for Public Integrity
      - Commercial speech & 1st Amendment, 25 July 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:52:04) (Electronic 6)
        With Peter Rofes, Marquette Law School
      - Liberal College Newspapers, 01 August 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:43:58) (Electronic 7)
        With Brian Auchterlonie, Collegiate Network executive director
      - Children's Media Watch Dog Group, 08 August 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:44:19) (Electronic 8)
        With James Steyer, Commonsense Media CEO
      - Television's Obsession With Scandal, 15 August 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:50:48) (Electronic 9)
        With Tim Cuprisin, Milwaukee Journal Sentinel columnist
      - What Would You Change?, 22 August 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:51:29) (Electronic 10)
      - Gays are 'In' on TV, 29 August 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:51:24) (Electronic 11)
        With Steve Johnson, Chicago Tribune TV critic
      - Press Box Red, 05 September 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:43:02) (Electronic 12)
        With Lester Rodney & Irwin Silber, author, "Press Box Red: The Story of Lester Rodney"
      - Fall TV Schedule, 12 September 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:45:02) (Electronic 13)
        With Joanne Weintraub, Milwaukee Journal Sentinel TV critic
      - BBC Bias, 19 September 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:45:06) (Electronic 14)
        With Michael Gonzalez, Wall Street Journal Europe
      - MoveOn's FCC Campaign, 26 September 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:43:46) (Electronic 15)
        With Eli Pariser, campaigns director of MoveOn.org
      - Big Lies, 03 October 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:43:49) (Electronic 16)
        With Joe Conason, author, "Big Lies: The Right Wing Propaganda Machine"
      - Most Censored Stories, 10 October 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:45:03) (Electronic 17)
        With Peter Phillips, director of Project Censored; Sonoma State University
      - Food Writing as Porn, 17 October 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:46:12) (Electronic 18)
        With Molly O'Neill, freelance writer
      - NYT & Objectivity, 24 October 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:46:30) (Electronic 19)
        With John Hess, author, "My Times: A Memoir of Dissent"
      - Jewish Sitcom, 31 October 2003, 2 digital audio files (0:12:42 and 0:31:45) (Electronic 20-21)
        With Vincent Brook, author of "Something Ain't Kosher Here"
      - Media Reform Conference Participants, 07 November 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:44:52) (Electronic 22)
        With J. Nicholas, J. Bouton, columnist, author, "Foul Ball"
      - Anchoring America: Changing Face of Network News, 14 November 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:45:00) (Electronic 23)
        With Jeff Alan, author, "Anchoring America: The Changing Face of Network News"
      - NPR Leans to the Left, 22 November 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:43:23) (Electronic 24)
        With Tim Graham, director of Media Analysis, Media Research Center
      - Open Line, 28 November 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:43:40) (Electronic 25)
      - Hottest Video Games & Gadgets, 28 November 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:44:32) (Electronic 26)
        With C. Taylor, W. Rothman, Time magazine writers
      - Pirate Radio Thesis, 12 December 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:43:29) (Electronic 27)
        With Lisa Nalbandian, WPR Milwaukee promotion manager
      - Prescription Drug Ads, 19 December 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:51:56) (Electronic 28)
        With Dr. Sydney Wolfe, director, Public Citizen's Health Research Group
      - Strom Thurmond's Daughter, 22 December 2003, 1 digital audio file (0:51:59) (Electronic 29)
        With Mary Mitchell, Chicago Sun Times columnist
      - Media Bias...Iraq, 26 December 2003, 2 digital audio files (0:06:33 and 0:36:50) (Electronic 30-31)
        With Notra Trulock, associate editor, Accuracy in Media Report
      - Why Media Suppressed FCC Plan, 02 January 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:45:08) (Electronic 32)
        With Charles Layton, freelance writer
      - BBC's Appeal in America, 09 January 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:36) (Electronic 33)
        With Laurie Robertson, editor, American Journalism Review
      - Media Training & Journalists Don't Get Answers, 16 January 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:30) (Electronic 34)
        With Trudy Lieberman, contributing editor to the CJR
      - Iowa Caucus Feelings, 19 January 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:39) (Electronic 35)
        With Diane Bystrom, director, Catt Center for Women & Politics, Iowa State University
      - Presidential Primaries Media Coverage, 23 January 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:04) (Electronic 36)
        With Craig Gilbert, Washington bureau chief, Milwaukee Journal Sentinel
      - Super Bowl Ads, 30 January 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:22) (Electronic 37)
        With Bernice Kanner, author, "The Super Bowl of Advertising"
      - The Smoking Gun.com, 06 February 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:45:09) (Electronic 38)
        With William Bastone, editor, "The Smoking Gun" web site
      - Unspinning Fox News' Bill O'Reilly, 13 February 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:46:41) (Electronic 39)
        With Peter Hart, author, "The Oh Really? Factor"
      - TV Coverage of Wisconsin Primary, 20 February 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:19) (Electronic 40)
        With Tim Cuprisin, columnist, Milwaukee Journal Sentinel
      - 2004 Academy Awards, 27 February 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:10) (Electronic 41)
        With Dave Luhrssen, Arts & Entertainment editor, Shepherd Express
      - The Death of TV as We Know It, 05 March 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:24) (Electronic 42)
        With Mike Drew, freelance writer
      - Is Business Journalism Up to Par?, 12 March 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:56) (Electronic 43)
        With Kathy Kristof, President, Soc. of Am. Business Editors & Writers
      - Did Media Screw Dean?, 19 March 2004, 2 digital audio files (0:19:02 and 0:24:25) (Electronic 44-45)
        With William Grieder, Journalist, The Nation
      - College Sex Column & Controversy, 26 March 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:22) (Electronic 46)
        With Claire Fuller, Sex Columnist, Lumberjack at No. AZ U
      - Bob Edwards Departure, 02 April 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:43) (Electronic 47)
        With Jack Mitchell, Former Director, Wisconsin Public Radio
      - Reporting on Weapons of Mass Destruction, 09 April 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:51:59) (Electronic 48)
        With Susan Moeller, Journalism Professor, U of Maryland
      - Ethics of Altered Digital Photography, 16 April 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:15) (Electronic 49)
        With Ken Light, Photojournalism Professor, UC-Berkeley
      - Open Line, 23 April 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:12) (Electronic 50)
      - Jailing of Arab Journalists, 30 April 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:45:03) (Electronic 51)
        With Christian Parenti, Ford Foundation Postdoctoral Fellow, CUNY
      - Propaganda, Free Speech, Opinion Control Since 9/11, 07 May 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:46:52) (Electronic 52)
        With Dr. Nancy Snow, author of "Information War"
      - Media's Coverage of Democratic Primary, 14 May 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:51:58) (Electronic 53)
        With Rachel Smolkin, senior writer, American Journalism Review
      - Status of Environmental Journalism, 21 May 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:12) (Electronic 54)
        With Dan Fagin, president, Society of Environmental Journalists
      - Under-Reporting of Poor & Working Classes, 28 May 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:28) (Electronic 55)
        With Brent Cunningham, editor, Columbia Journalism Review
      - Under-Reporting of Religious Issues, 04 June 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:45:08) (Electronic 56)
        With Gal Beckerman, assistant editor, Columbia Journalism Review
      - Interview with Ben Bagdikian, 11 June 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:29) (Electronic 57)
        With Ben Bagdikian, author, "The New Media Monopoly"
      - Non-College Bound Students, 22 June 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:52:47) (Electronic 58)
        With Marty Nemko, author, "The All-in-One College Guide"
      - How Did 'Fahrenheit 9-11' Influence You?, 02 July 2004, 2 digital audio files (0:37:24 and 0:06:34) (Electronic 59-60)
      - Future of Broadcast Regulation, 09 July 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:30) (Electronic 61)
        With Nicholas Johnson, former FCC Commissioner
      - Media Coverage of 9-11 Commission & Post-War Iraq, 16 July 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:07) (Electronic 62)
        With Tim Graham, Media Research Center, director of Media Analysis
      - Media Not Reporting Candidate's Accuracy, 23 July 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:26) (Electronic 63)
        With Bryan Keefer, co-author of "All The President's Spin"
      - Media Coverage of Democratic Convention, 30 July 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:59) (Electronic 64)
        With Tim Cuprisin, media columnist, Milwaukee Journal Sentinel
      - Media Coverage of the South, 06 August 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:45:17) (Electronic 65)
        With Jacob Levenson, author, "Divining Dixie"
      - Web Radio, 13 August 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:30) (Electronic 66)
        With Patrick Conley, co-founder, "80's Airwaves"
      - Tales from the Left Coast, 20 August 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:45:03) (Electronic 67)
        With James Hirsen, NewsMax columnist
      - Watergate Revisited, 27 August 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:35) (Electronic 68)
        With Mark Feldstein, Director, School of Media & Public Affairs, George Washington University
      - Republican Convention Coverage, 03 September 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:38) (Electronic 69)
      - Upcoming TV Season, 10 September 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:59) (Electronic 70)
        With Joanne Weintraub, TV critic, Milwaukee Journal Sentinel
      - Lack of Coverage on Homeland Security, 17 September 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:45:26) (Electronic 71)
        With Trudy Lieberman, contributing editor, CJR
      - Controversy re: CBS & Bush's Military Files, 24 September 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:24) (Electronic 72)
        With Joe Strupp, senior editor, "Editor & Publisher"
      - Candidates Control Presidential Debate, 01 October 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:42:54) (Electronic 73)
        With Christopher Shaw, Organizing Director, Open Debate
      - Japanese Media Warning to American Media, 08 October 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:44:56) (Electronic 74)
        With Adam Gamble, author, "A Public Betrayed"
      - Howard Stern's Move to Sirius, 15 October 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:31) (Electronic 75)
        With Tim Cuprisin, media columnist, Milwaukee Journal-Sentinel
      - Protection of Confidential Sources, 22 October 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:45:32) (Electronic 76)
        With Gene Policinski, First Amendment Center, executive director
      - Media Presidential Coverage Open Line, 29 October 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:43:36) (Electronic 77)
      - Media's Failure on WMD, 05 November 2004, 1 digital audio file (0:46:29) (Electronic 78)
        With Todd Gitlin, columnist, Mother Jones Magazine